Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today the whole entire goal
is to go through how to fill
in molecular orbital diagrams.
So what we're going to be doing
is we're gonna go through some of
the basic ideas of how this works.
We're gonna be learning how
to predict when something's
paramagnetic, diamagnetic, how
to fill in bond order, and how to
count our bonding and anti-bonding.
So as we go through this, the whole
idea here is that it's exactly
like electron configuration.
We're gonna be f uh, following
the Al principle, Huns rule and
the poly exclusion principle.
Same ideas that you would
before, but instead with the
molecular orbital picture instead.
So it allows us to predict all
those different properties.
So when we're gonna get to go through
this now, depending on, uh, your
professor who you're learning from.
All of 'em are a little bit different.
So sometimes they'll give you the
orbitals and you just gotta fill
them in and do your calculations.
Others can be a little different and
be harder, and you have to be able
to predict them and know the actual
understanding behind it typically depends
on what level of course you're in.
So for example, my general
chemistry courses we're always, I
usually always give the diagrams
and they just have to fill in.
So we're gonna look at the bonding,
anti-bonding orbitals and use
that to be able to determine
what the bond strength is.
Which allows us to figure
out what is the bond order.
Now with bond order,
it's just an equation.
Alls we're doing is counting,
well, how many electrons are
in the bonding orbitals, right?
So the ones without stars, and
then we're subtracting it from
the anti-bonding orbitals.
So the ones with stars.
Okay?
So that's what we're doing is no
stars minus stars divided by two.
Now, this is where some of the bond
order numbers came from before.
It's the true reason where it comes from.
So it's single bonds are always one.
Double bonds are two,
triple bonds are three.
If it can't bond, that's a zero.
And if you ever see a non integer
number, that's typically meaning that
it could have resonance behind it.
Uh, for especially if you think
of like really large structures,
uh, or it's telling you that the
bond is weakened or stronger.
So like for example, if you have
a three like that, that's probably
your strongest bond being citri on
or for most normal, uh, molecules.
But if you have like a 2.5, that's telling
you it's a little weaker than three.
So the strongest in this, for
most cases, is gonna be three.
The weakest is gonna be, you know,
one or 0.5 if you can get a 0.5.
So it's always kind of, it's a scale
when we're talking about energy, right?
So that's what we're gonna gonna try
to do as we go through these examples.
So let's take a look.
The first thing is, is when we're
trying to go through these examples,
is how exactly do the orbitals work?
Well, if you remember from my previous
video, it, it was all about if you
have two atomic orbitals going in.
You're gonna get two
molecular orbitals coming out.
So generally, the way that we end
up kind of looking at this is that
the two orbital are going to try to
combine with each other, but as a
result, the whole idea here as well,
the phases of the orbitals, they're
gonna both construct and deconstruct.
So meaning it is going to split.
Into essentially two different
molecular orbitals as a result of
these interacting with one another.
So what kind of orbitals?
What would we make?
Well, if we have, let's say s an S
orbital and an S orbital coming together,
well, what can we kind of predict?
Well, we see overlap between both of 'em.
So what does that mean is we're
gonna have a sigma orbital for both.
So the lower energy is gonna be
your bonding orbital, and then
the higher is your anti-bonding.
So that's when we put the little
star just to say that, hey, this
is higher in energy, so it's going
off of what we talked about before.
Now this is where we take the
electrons from valence for each atom.
So we have the one on the right, and then
we also have the one on the left as well.
And we're just gonna fill
them into the middle.
So we're gonna fill 'em
in from the bottom first.
So I'm gonna take one electron from the
hydrogen on the left, and then we'll
fill in one from the one on the right.
So how about this?
We'll do a different color for it.
So essentially they're both gonna
end up filling in from each side,
and it's going to be creating
a molecular orbital between it.
So there's a couple questions
we can end up answering here.
So the first one is bond order.
Okay, so the whole idea of bond
orders we're counting, bonding
electrons, minusing it from
anti-bonding, dividing by two.
Well, in this one, right?
If we were to look at our, our
orbital that is filled at the moment,
well, the only thing here is that
we have how many bonding electrons?
Well, we got two, right?
So there's two in bonding.
Now, how many of them are in anti-bonding?
Well, if we look closely, we see
a whole lot of nothing, right?
So what is the math gonna be there?
Two minus zero divided by two is
gonna be equal to a bond order of one.
I. Does that make sense?
Well, if you were to draw the
Lewis structure, it's H single
bonded to H, so yeah, that's great.
So, hey, it works.
We like that.
All right.
Now is it paramagnetic or diamagnetic?
Well, diamagnetic was all about
if everything is paired up, it
would be diamagnetic, which it is.
So this, so hydrogen gas is not magnetic.
Oh, sad days.
That's okay.
Alright, now the next part is
molecular electron configuration.
Which is a little different.
It's, but it's similar to electron
configuration where if you remember, you
did like one S two two S, two two P six.
The only difference here is you're
counting what's in each of those orbitals.
So for example, our first orbital
was Sigma one s, and we're counting
how many electrons we have in
there, which is a total of two.
Right.
And if we had more, we would, we
would fill them all in as well.
So that's just our
first one and that's it.
Let's do another one, right?
Let's keep trying to fill this in.
All right, so for this one, we got
helium and helium connecting together.
So with two noble gases,
can they bond together?
Let's try to take a look.
So the whole idea, right?
We have our sigma orbitals
already labeled in, right?
Two atomic orbitals.
One s and one s go in and it should
be two molecular orbitals come out.
So alls we're gonna do is we're gonna
take one electron from the left.
We're gonna take one from the
right, and we're gonna take
another one from the left.
And another one from the right.
Combine 'em all together.
And what do we got?
We got two in the anti-bonding.
Two in the bonding.
So how do we do our math?
Well, it's gonna be two
minus two divided by two.
So as a result, it's gonna
probably be very undefined or zero.
So what does that mean is that
we do not have a bond that makes.
That should make sense, right?
Noble gases, they don't want
to interact with each other.
They generally only do dispersion forces.
They can't do much else.
So our bond order in this
case is going to be zero.
Now, is it dia, diamagnetic
or paramagnetic?
Once again, we still do not
have any unaired electrons,
so it's gonna be dye magnetic.
Again, helium is not magnetic.
So if we were gonna fill in our
electron configuration, well, we're
going through all the orbitals we have.
We had Sigma one s and then we
also had Sigma one s with that's
anti-bonding with a little star.
So now we're gonna fill in how
many electrons we have in each.
So we got two in the first
one, two in the second one.
And we're just kind of summarizing
this big diagram that's up there.
That's the whole idea of let's
do the next diatomic that could
form based on the P Act table.
Let's see what else is possible.
Okay, so lithium tube, we're
moving up the P Act table, meaning
we're on the second valence level.
Meaning we have one valence
electron for each of the
different elements that are here.
So we got one and two s
for each of the elements.
So we're gonna combine them both together.
So one's coming from the lithium on the
left, the other one's gonna combine,
come from the lithium on the other side.
So if we're gonna calculate our bond
order, alls we're gonna do is it's
two in the anti or two in the bonding.
Zero in the anti-bonding divide by two.
So what do we get is a bond order of one.
So it should be a single bond.
Hey, it's following our bond trends.
And that makes sense.
So this is where the bond trends
or properties are coming from, not
just something that scientists are
like, Hey, student memorize, right?
No, it's actually coming from somewhere.
Um, as we're kind of going through it,
it's gonna be diamagnetic once again.
'cause we still don't
have anything paired up.
Now if we were gonna try to
summarize this, right now we're
in, uh, Sigma two s and we have
a total of two electrons in here.
You could, it, depending on,
uh, you can summarize it even to
include the one s from before.
So that is something that it, it, you
could include everything as like a
more of a complete notation as well.
So based on this diagram, we just
have Sigma two s. If you want to be
thorough about it, you could say Sigma
one S two, Sigma one s, uh, star two.
So taking the helium part and then
combining it with our lithium here.
So bringing in all the different orbitals,
all the mo orbitals that are interacting.
Alright.
Can Beryllium two exist
where we go through this one?
So first is if we were to fill
in our electrons for our valence
level, we have two valence
electrons for beryllium, right?
Checking your POC table.
Second column.
So if we were to fill in these electrons,
we're gonna be giving two electrons
from each atom into both orbitals.
So once again, if we were to do the
math here, we can see two in the bonding
on the bottom, two in the anti-bonding
on the top, and we're dividing that by
the two nuclei, right, that are here.
So what do we got?
We got a big old zero.
So what does that mean?
That means no bond.
That's gonna be super unstable.
It's not gonna happen, right?
So no bond is gonna be ma being made here.
It's unstable, is what that says.
So as a result, um, being that
there's no bond, generally we
wouldn't assign Diamagnetic or
paramagnetic, but based off what we
have there might as well be thorough.
That would be diamagnetic in terms
of our electron configuration.
This one, I would really pay
attention to what every teacher does.
Sometimes they will include the one
s like I did on the example before.
Some will just only go
off of what you have here.
Usually I'm okay with you just going
off what's being shown in a diagram,
so, but everybody's a little different.
Depends on how much you have.
So we would have Sigma two S two,
and then Sigma two s with a star.
A two.
And keep in mind, if you had to
do the entire thing, you would add
the configuration for one s and
one s anti binding with a star on
it, and you'd have all of them.
Um, one other thing to kind of keep
in mind, everybody does teach us
sometimes different, some people
don't use a sigma symbol as well.
So as I'm kind of reading about this
and checking different textbooks,
just to be thorough, I do sometimes
see that people will use just the
letter s, not for the S orbital.
But for Sigma, so keep that in mind.
If anyone ever sees like Sigma
two S two or S two S star
two, it's referring to sigma.
So it's just another way.
Same with PI using a P. So it's
another way that it, it can be written
for these different structures.
So keep that in mind.
If you're someone that's like, I
don't recognize any of this, it's
just another way of viewing it.
Right.
Let's take another look.
Look at another one.
All right.
With boron, this is where it
starts getting more complicated.
Typically, with mo theory, we
don't usually go above neon too.
Um, which is like on that second row
being the, on the third level, that's
when you get access to the de orbitals
and it gets really complicated where
you really would probably need the,
the help with advanced computing to
figure out all the diatomic elements
and exactly what do they look like.
So the first thing just to
point out, right, you can see
the two s is exactly the same.
So if we were doing boron two, well
we would fill in our valence electrons
just like we would before, right?
So there's three valence electrons.
So we're gonna fill in those
different valence electrons here.
So, so when we're doing this one, the
bottom one, let's do that real quick.
Being that's just following
our normal thing, right?
We see that everything's
gonna be filled up.
So when you have atomic orbitals
filled, you kind of might be
noticing the trend is that the ular
orbitals are gonna be filled too.
Now when we get to the P block,
that's when it gets a little harder.
And the big thing is, well, it's
because there was more possible, you
had six electrons that were there.
So if you think the hybridization, well,
what could you make with the P block?
Is that, well, what's possible
is you could always have a sigma.
A Pi and a Pi that are always
gonna be possible with each of
those orbitals that are there.
So you always make one
sigma and then two Pis.
So if we're to go through this, well, the
first thing is, is that the Pi orbitals
end up being lower in energy at first, or
the first three elements in the P block.
So for boron.
Uh, for, uh, carbon and
nitrogen, they're all lower.
And the whole reason for that was if
you keep 'em, if you remember, for
electron configuration, you filled
one electron in its own room all by
itself in the electron configuration,
though it was way hapPir as a result.
So with this one, we're gonna
actually have one in each of its
own little orbitals that are here.
And what are they?
Well, essentially we're gonna have five
or sign, not five pi ppy and then Pi pz.
And now the reason why you have
both is that they're both parallel.
No matter what direction they're
degenerate, meaning they're
equivalent to one another.
Okay?
So it's kind of going off your electron
configuration where they're all the same.
The only one that's a little bit
different is the Sigma PX orbital, or
sorry, I should put a two PX and two
py for all these is the sigma bond
actually ends up being a little bit
lower in energy or higher in energy
for these first three elements.
And then we'll kind of continue saying,
okay, uh, we have Sigma Star two PY or
PI two PY star, and then PI Star two pz.
Then we have Sigma two
pz, also with a star.
So we have the anti-bonding all the way
at the top, the bonding at the bottom.
So we filled in those lonely
electrons at the bottom.
So we're trying to
calculate our bond order.
What are we gonna do is we're gonna, once
again count all the bonding orbitals.
So we got, we would have
two in the Sigma to us.
Then we'd have another
two in the Pi group.
So what would that be?
Is that, it's gonna be four, and
then we have two in the anti-bonding.
So with the little stars,
so it'd be four minus two.
So we're just looking for the stars.
It's kind of one way to look through it.
We're gonna divide that by two.
So what is that gonna be?
It's gonna be two divided by two, and
that's gonna be a bond order of one.
So between boron and boron, we can
only make a single bond if we were
trying to try to connect to these guys
together, would be the entire idea here.
So in terms of, is this one
magnetic or paramagnetic?
Well, we actually have lonely electrons
for the first time up in the top.
So what would that mean is that,
well, if you had D boron, this
would actually be paramagnetic.
So it would be something
that could be magnetized.
So if we were to try to fill in
our orbitals, so we have Sigma
two S, two of them in there.
We have Sigma two s Star,
two of them in there.
And then the next one, how do
we do these PI ones, what we'd
say PI two, PY comma PI two, pz.
And then, and the reason why we're
doing that is because they're equivalent
all the way up to the top there.
So what we're doing is we're just gonna
say that, hey, we got two electrons in
there and it can fit a total of four.
So that can, that can go up a lot higher
because we're talking about two orbitals.
So every orbital can hold two electrons.
So we'd have, we'd have more
electrons that can go in there.
All right, so our last one's
gonna be all about oxygen.
So with this one, it's gonna
be a little bit different than
what we were seeing before.
You can see that the, if you kind
of remember the order of how you
might have wrote down the orbitals
actually changes of the structure.
So this is where we start
seeing SP mixing happening.
And this was actually occurring
on the previous orbitals too.
I just didn't mention it yet.
And it's all because of how the electron
configuration is filled in for oxygen.
So if you can think of the valence level.
So let's say if we did the one
on the left, so we had the two
in S, and then we would fill np.
Now when we were talking about like boron,
nitrogen, and carbon, we would fill all
the way across and everything had its
own bedroom, right when it came to all
the individual electrons that are there.
With that entire idea there,
everything having its own little
elect, own little room, it would
cause actually a, a want to do more
Pi bonding versus doing sigma bonding.
But now that we have this extra electron
here, it now wants to do sigma bonding.
So the orbital move down so we can
see the sigma two PX is actually
lower in energy and the pi orbitals
are actually now in the middle.
So if we were to fill this
in, right, so we'll put the
other oxygen on the right here.
So filling in all of our electrons.
What we're gonna do is we'll fill in
everything from on the, in the Sigma area,
or sorry, not the Sigma Sigma two s area.
We see that completely cancels out.
Everything's filled up.
Now we're gonna fill in all of our
electrons for in each orbital from
our left atom, and then we'll fill
in all of them for the right as well.
So once we do that, we can see that,
okay, we have all six electrons for
blue, all six electrons for red, I
think, or it should be everything.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Yeah,
so we have oh, 3, 2, 1.
So we have all the electrons accounted
for here, so we got all six on both sides.
So that's great.
Now, the one thing to point out is,
oh, up top, you actually have some
unpaired electrons that are here,
which, if you remember, if you watch
my previous video about this was all
about that, hey, if we have this, uh.
These, this oxygen here is that
we should actually be able to
see this magnetic property.
So if I'm gonna fast forward here
and I, and I pour oxygen between the
two magnets, we're gonna see oxygen
getting stuck between the poles, and
that's because of those electrons.
So there are two unaired
electrons, it's just in the
molecular orbital is where it is.
Ah, who would've thought?
So, it's just a little bit
more complicated, right, than
anything that we normally look at.
But it is something that
it, it is actually there.
So if we were trying to go through
our math here, so doing bond orders.
So how many bond orders do we have?
So let's see.
We got, we got one, we got two,
then we have three and four.
Then we got 5, 6, 7, 8.
So we have eight.
Then for anti-bonding, we have
two, then we have three and four.
So it'd be eight minus
four divided by two.
And what does that tell us is that we'll
have a bond order of two, which backs
up our double bonded Lewis structure.
So it helps tell us that
yes, we have a double bond.
We can prove it with the theory, then
we could fill in everything else, right?
We know it's paramagnetic because
we're we're seeing the magnetization.
We were able to observe it.
We can explain the result.
Now, we could fill in all of our orbitals.
So we had Sigma two s,
two Sigma two s, star two.
Then we had Sigma two, PX two,
and then we had, uh, PI two py, PI two pz.
So if you keep in mind that one
was where we did PI two py, PI
two pz, and that would be a four.
And then, and that's referring to
these four electrons right here.
And then we'll have the PI two
ppy, PI two, PZ two because
there's only two electrons.
So let's kind of move all this
over a little bit and make some
room and that will be our last one.
So this is something that it is quite
a lot right to try to wrap our heads
around, but it is totally manageable.
It's just another way of
doing electron configuration.
So just to end this right
question for you, right?
And let's think of what bond order
does N two have and do you, and after
you draw the orbitals, is it power or
is it dye magnetic or, and or N two.
So could you do that?
So if you're my student, that's gonna
be your, your questions about the popup
and if you are watching this video feel
you free to put your answer down in the
comments section, what you think it is,
and I'll tell you if it's right or wrong.
All right, let's take, thank
you so much for watching and I
appreciate you and I hope you
have a wonderful rest of your day.
Bye now.